Finding Aid for the Leonard Kleinrock Papers LSC.2337
UCLA Library Special Collections
Leonard Kleinrock papers
1957-1980
UCLA Library Special Collections
United States. Advanced Research Projects Agency
LSC.2337
2.4 Linear Feet (6 document boxes)
Leonard Kleinrock, UCLA faculty in Computer Science since 1964. He received his BA from CCNY and MA and PhD from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Kleinrock ran the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) Network Measurement Center (NMC), the first ARPANET node. The Kleinrock Papers include: McGraw-Hill Publishers correspondence; technical notes; Advanced Research Projects Agency progress reports; publications materials; Interface Message processor logs; SPADE administrative notes; Miscellaneous Network Notes; ARPANET Satellite System notes; Packet Radio Temp notes; and Networks Use Technical notes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Leonard Kleinrock.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9981550033606533
Biography/History
Leonard Kleinrock was born in New York City on June 13, 1934. He received a Bachelor of Electrical Engineering degree in 1957 from the City College of New York, and a master's degree and a doctorate (Ph.D.) in electrical engineering and computer science from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in 1959 and 1963 respectively. Kleinrock developed a mathematical theory of packet networks, the technology underpinning the Internet, while a graduate student at MIT in the period from 1960-1962. Kleinrock has served as a Professor of Computer Science at the University of California Los Angeles (UCLA) since 1963. The first host-to-host ARPANET connection occurred in the UCLA Network Measurement Center run by Kleinrock (3420 Boelter Hall at UCLA) when his SDS Sigma 7 Host computer became the first node of the Internet in September 1969. From UCLA, Kleinrock directed the transmission of the first message to pass over the Internet on October 29, 1969. Kleinrock served with programmer Charley Kline as Chairman of the Computer Science department at UCLA from 1991-1995 and is a Distinguished Professor of Computer Science at UCLA. During his tenure at UCLA, Kleinrock supervised the research for 48 Ph.D. students and numerous M.S. students who formed a core of advanced networking experts. Kleinrock has published over 250 papers and authored six books on a wide array of subjects, including packet switching networks, packet radio networks, local area networks, broadband networks, gigabit networks, nomadic computing, intelligent software agents, performance evaluation, and peer-to-peer networks. Kleinrock received numerous awards including the prestigious National Medal of Science in 2008 for his contributions to the mathematical theory of modern data networks and for the functional specification of packet switching. In 2012, Kleinrock was inducted into the Internet Hall of Fame by the Internet Society.
Scope and Content
Leonard Kleinrock's papers include: correspondence for publication of his book, Communication nets: Stochastic message flow and delay. (McGraw-Hill, 1964); technical notes from his design work at Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC); and materials from the Network Measurement Center (NMC) which discuss the early development of the Internet in the United States during the 1960s and 1970s. Materials from the NMC consist of notes and papers from the first ARPANET node at UCLA. The papers include Interface Message Processor Logs documenting the first message on the ARPANET and progress reports to ARPA. The notes detail the technical evolution of the ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) and the ALOHA system including Request for Comments (RFC) and a Bolt Beranek and Newman Quarterly Technical Report. There are also Administrative notes from the SPADE Group, responsible for the Sigma 7 system software and programming support for the ARPA project, consisting of Agenda, meeting notes, and bug lists including NUTS notes referring to the TENEX program. Finally there are notes detailing Packet Radio Communication and its application for distribution of data consisting of meeting notes, academic papers, and protocol notes. Arrangement is by note number first and then chronologically providing a technical progression for the history of the ARPANET.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
1. McGraw-Hill Publishers Correspondence
2. Technical Notes
3. Progress Reports to the Advanced Research Projects Agency
4. Publications
5. Interface Message Processor Logs
6. SPADE Administrative Notes
7. Miscellaneous Network Notes
8. ARPANET System Satellite Notes and Request for Comments
9. Packet Radio Temp Notes
10. Networks Use Technical (NUTS) Notes
Manuals and documents are ordered chronologically within series. Notes are ordered by note number first and then chronologically to reflect the original arrangement which provides a progression for the history of the ARPANET.
Existence and Location of Copies
Selected items were digitized for the Kleinrock Internet History Center (KIHC) Digital Collections:http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/internethistory/.
ARPANET (Computer network).; Internet -- History -- United States -- Archives.; Packet switching (Data transmission) -- Archives.; Digital Equipment Corporation; Kleinrock, Leonard--Archives.; Postel, Jonathan Bruce; United States. Advanced Research Projects Agency
- Series 1: McGraw-Hill Publishers Correspondence, 1963-1965
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials relating to the publication of Kleinrock's Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) Ph.D. Thesis Communication nets: Stochastic message flow and delay. (McGraw-Hill, 1964) and includes: letters, memorandum, and proofs.
  - McGraw-Hill Publishers - General Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - McGraw-Hill Publishers - General Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Technical Notes, 1957-1963
  Technical notes from Kleinrock's research. Includes notes on the Variable Delay Unit one of the first Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC) products, the Magnetic Films Seminar at MIT, and the TX-2 network simulation program. Includes notes, papers, schematics and simulation data in graphs and computer printouts.
  - Variable delay unit original notes, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Magnetic Films Seminar at MIT, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - TX-2 Simulation Specifications, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - TX-2 Miscellaneous program and Simulation Notes, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - TX-2 Numerical Data from Simulation, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - TX-2 Network Simulation Program Notes Part A, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - TX-2 Network Simulation Program Notes Part B, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - TX-2 Network Simulation Program Notes part C, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unspecified material - Computer Printouts, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Progress Reports to the Advanced Research Projects Agency (ARPA), 1963-1973
  Progress reports to the Advanced Research Projects Agency during the period of the early development of the ARPANET. Includes technical reports, contracts, and correspondence.
  - "Progress Report to the Advanced Research Projects Agency" (1 of 3), 1963-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Progress Report to the Advanced Research Projects Agency" (2 of 3), 1963-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Progress Report to the Advanced Research Projects Agency" (3 of 3), 1963-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series 4: Publications, 1963-1975
  - Publication Outline - "Communication Nets stochastic message and delay", circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publication Draft - "Communication Nets stochastic message and delay", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
  - Publication Proof - "Communication Nets stochastic message and delay", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Publication Galley - "Communication Nets stochastic message and delay", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - American Federation of Information Processing Societies (AFIPS) Conference Proceedings, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - List of "Material in archive", circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series 5: Interface Message Processor Logs, 1969-1979
  Handwritten logs from the UCLA Network Measurement Center showing, the first ARPANET node, including the first host-to-host connection (October 1969).
  - Interface Message Processor Log, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Interface Message Processor Log, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Interface Message Processor Log, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Interface Message Processor Log, 1974-1976; 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series 6: SPADE Administrative Notes, System Manuals, and User Guides, 1969-1973
  Administrative notes, system manuals and user guides from the UCLA SPADE Group responsible for SDS Sigma 7 system software, Sigma Experimental System (SEX), and programming support for the ARPA project. The SDS Sigma 7 system was the first system to connect to the ARPANET at UCLA, the first ARPANET node.
  - Subseries 6.1: SPADE Administrative Notes, 1969-1972
    SPADE administrative notes including: Fortran programming language implementation, early implementation of the Telnet network protocol, network measurement, Network Control Program (NCP) development, and the Sigma Experimental System (SEX) operating system for the SDS Sigma 7.
    - Index of SPADE Notes, 10 Nov 1969-7 Jun 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - SPADE Administrative Notes, 1-45, 10 Oct 1969-11 Aug 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Scope and Contents
      Notes of interest: SPADE Admin Note 1: "the SPADE Group" (discusses group creation) SPADE Admin Note 20: SPADE Meeting note (name change GORDO to SEX, Sigma EXchange System)
      Missing notes: 6, 36
    - SPADE Administrative Notes, 46-80, 18 August 1970 to 10 February 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Scope and Content
      Notes of interest: SPADE Admin Note 53: John Postel diagram on SEX implementation SPADE Admin Note 63: NW Measurements meeting (9 IMPS on network) SPADE Admin Note 69: SPADE Meeting Note (early note on Telnet and mailboxes) SPADE Admin Note 71: Progress report (SPADE group divides: SEX, Network measurement, and coordination of network development) SPADE Admin Note 76: The Plan (diagram of workflow for 3 month plan for network, systems, graphics, documents)
    - SPADE Administrative Notes 81-110, 12 Feburary 1971 to 28 May 1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Note of interest:
      SPADE Admin Note 88: SPADE Meeting (discusses making net history with live user of BBN TENEX via telnet); SPADE Admin Note 94: Crashes and what to do about them Missing note: 105
    - SPADE Administrative Notes 111-140, 4 June 1971- 20 August 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Notes of interest:
      SPADE Admin Note 116: (comments such as "catch up on missed meals, sleep and showers, gives slice of life); SPADE Admin Note 118: (notes on design process for SEX console)
      SPADE administrative notes 120, 134, and 139 are missing.
    - SPADE Administrative Notes, 141-170, 26 August 1971 - 18 November 1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      SPADE Admin Note 141: Bug List (example of computer printout for bug reports)
      SPADE Admin Note 160: SPADE Meeting (L. Roberts report "caused a stir")
    - SPADE Administrative Notes, 171-199, 19 November 1971 - 10 March 1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      SPADE Admin Note 176: SPADE Meeting (diagram of 3 months system tasks/development)
      SPADE Admin Note 178: SPADE Meeting (diagram for USER host)
      SPADE Admin Note 180: SPADE Meeting (diagram Sigma 7 software)
      SPADE Admin Note 197: SPADE Meeting (diagram CCN model)
      SPADE administrative note 188 is missing.
    - SPADE Notes to Secretaries 14, Printing Documents at UCLA-CCN, 3 April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 6.2: System Manuals and User Guides, 1973
    System manuals and user guides for the Network Information Center (NIC) and Sigma Experimental System (SEX).
    - Network Information Center User Guide, 9 Jan 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - SEX Beginner's Guide, 20 Jan 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Document #8 SEX User's Manual, 27 Jan 1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Brief Description of Some Arpanet Resources and Their Uses, 12 Dec 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series 7: Miscellaneous Network Notes, 1969-1978
  - Misc NW Notes, 1-16, 24 November 1969-2 February 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Notes of interest are:
    Misc NW Note 10 UCLA Computer Science Site profile
    Misc NW Note 12 Bibliography of Literature on Computer Networking
    Missing Misc NW notes 3-8, 11, 15.
  - Misc NW Notes, 17-39, 26 March 1971 - 18 March 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Misc NW Note 17 Guide to Network Working Group/Request for Comments
    Misc NW Note 18 ARPA Net
    Missing Misc NW Notes 25-31, 34.
  - Letter: BBN Connected to Arpanet Site #5, 30 March 1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Protocol Spec NIC #7101 Official Initial Connection Protocol, 11 Jun 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Protocol Spec NIC #7103 Official Telnet Logger-Initial Connection Protocol Document #3, 15 Jun 1971 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - IFIP/INWG Meeting, NPL, 12 May 1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - IFIP/INWG Results of Questionnaire on Distributed Processing Systems, 22 May 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series 8: ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes and Request for Comments, 1972-1976
  ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, Request for Comments, and a related BBN technical Report from the UCLA Network Measurement Center. The ARPANET Satellite System was a data communications network based on packet switching technology using ALOHA system methods such as asynchronous random access.
  - Subseries 8.1: ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, 1972-1973
    - List of ARPANET Satellite System Notes, 6 Apr 1973 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - ASS Note Index, 14 Aug, 5 Dec 1973 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Peak Rate for Satellite Stations, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - ARPANET Satellite System Misc. Inserts, [1972] (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, 2-15, 20 March -11 September 1972 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Papers of interest:
      ASS Note 8: "Aloha packet System with and without slots and capture" by Lawrence G. Roberts
      ASS Note 11: "A brief Simulation of the Dynamics of and Aloha system with slots" by Randy Rettberg
      ASS Note 12: "Analytic Results for the ARPANET Satellite. System Model Including the Effects of the Retransmission Delay Distribution" by Leonard Kleinrock and Simon Lam
      Missing ASS Note 1
    - ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, 16-25, 18 October 1972- 20 November 1972 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      ASS Note 17: "Approximations in the Infinite Population Model of the ARPANET Satellite System." by Kleinrock and Lam
      ASS Note 21: "A Comparison of BBN ALOHA and Idealized Slotted Aloha"
      Missing ASS notes 40 and 49.
    - ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, 26-32, 15 November 1972 - 27 December 1972 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      ASS Note 27: "Analytic Results with the Addition of one Large User." by Kleinrock and Lam
    - ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, 33-39, 26 December 1972 - July 1973 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, 41-51, 29 April 1973 - 7 September 1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Note to ASS Note Recipients, 20 September 1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - ARPANET Satellite System (ASS) Notes, 52-53, 57, 8 November 1973 - 1973 (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
      Missing ASS Notes 54, 55, 56, 58, and 59.
    - Corrections to ASS Note 59, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 8.2: Request for Comments (RFC) and BBN Technical Report, 1972-1976
    Request for Comments detailing the use of space transmission links in the ARPANET including Echo and Discard processes, and a proposed standard for socket numbers for network protocols. The BBN report describes their work on the Packet Radio Satellite project.
    - RFC: 346 - 349, 30 May 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - BBN PSP Quarterly Technical Report for May, June, July 1976, 18 Sep 1976 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series 9: Packet Radio Temp Notes, 1972-1980
  Packet Radio Temp Notes detailing packet radio communication and its use for distribution of data, and Protocol notes describing flow control principles for packet switched network protocols.
  - Subseries 9.1: Packet Radio Temp Notes, 1972-1974
    - Packet Radio Temporary Note Index, 6 Mar 1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Report: First Packet Radio Working Group Meeting, circa 1972 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Packet Radio Temp Notes, 1-10, 14 December 1972-December 1972 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      PRTN 1: "Packet Radio Meeting of December 12-13, 1972" (defines terms, IDs and involved institutions)
      The following Packet Radio Temp notes are missing: 8, 9.
    - Packet Radio Temp Notes, 11-20, 15 January 1973 - 16 February 1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      PRTN 11: "Routing in Packet Radio Systems. Controlled Flooding Using Handover Numbers" by Kleinrock and Tobagi
      The following Packet Radio Temp notes are missing: 18, 19, 21.
    - Packet Radio Temp Notes, 22-30, 5-28 Feburary 1973 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      PRTN 24: "Throughput in Carrier-Sense (AutoSlot) Packet Radio Systems" by by Kleinrock and Tobagi
      PRTN 29: Facsimile Data Format by L. Schaefer
    - Extended Directory of Network Groups, 18 May 1973 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 9.2: Protocol Notes, 1974-1980
    - Protocol Note #8 Flow Control, 28 Oct 1974 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - INWG Protocol Note #12 An Integrated Approach to Network Protocols, Nov 1974 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Protocol Note #17 Packet Loss and Its Recovery in a Packet Switched Network, Feb 1975 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - INWG Protocol Note #28 Some Constraints and Tradeoffs in the Design of Network Communications (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - INWG Protocol Note #21 A Proposal for Fragmenting Packets in Internetworking, Apr 1975 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - PRTN 22 Activity Signalling and Improved HOP Acknowledgements, Jan 1980 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Series 10: Networks Use Technical (NUTS) Notes, 1973-1974
  Networks Use Technical (NUTS) notes including: a new Mail Subsystem, the NLS system, accounts for the UCLA Network Measurement Center (NMC), the SEXDOC program, and BBN Tenex programs such as CCNJOB, an interactive Tenex program for document printing and reading SDS Sigma 7 SEX tapes. The NUTS notes refer to accounts, systems, program and the BBN TENEX project that provided programs used by the SPADE group.
  - NUTS Notes 1-4, 5-6 April 1973 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - NUTS Notes 14 - 16, 5 April - 2 May 1974 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - NUTS Notes 21-22, 4-5 Apr 1974 (Box 6, Folder 23)